<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
Copyright 2001-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
limitations under the License.
-->

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Turbine 3</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

  <section name="Weekly Status Report: 8 March 2002">
     <p>
     </p>
   </section>

  <section name="Turbine 2.2">
     <p>
       Things are still on schedule for the release of Turbine 2.2 Beta 1
       on the 18th of March. Eric Dobbs has volunteer to help with the
       integration of Fulcrum into Turbine 2.2 so there will be two of
       us working on a solution. Once this is done we can release and
       let people give things a whirl.
     </p>
     <p>
       The services code in Turbine 2.2 will be declared dead, in the
       same fashion as Torque code in 2.2 has, so there will be a migration document
       for those planning on moving their 2.2 services forward to
       Fulcrum. I will also try to get a transformation descriptor
       together for use with the transformation tool in Maven to take
       care of the tedious changes like import statements and the like.
     </p>
   </section>

   <section name="Progress on Maven">
     <p>
       We managed to work out most of the project extensibility issues in that
       it is now easy for a project to have its specific targets coexist with
       the maven targets that come as are part of the generated build system.
     </p>
     <p>
       Pete has made a DVSL stylesheet that produces an attractive page
       displaying the JUnit tests.
     </p>
     <p>
       I've done some work on a tool that will analyse a project's existing
       JAR file and determine dependencies on other projects. At the moment
       I know what the invidual class dependencies are by using bytecode
       analysis and now I have to map those class dependencies to projects
       in order to produce an accurate project descriptor with full
       dependencies listed.
     </p>
     <p>
       I have converted the Texen Ant task into a bean so that it can be
       used from the command line so I hope to have a command line tool that
       will produce a comprehensive Maven build system along with
       required project descriptor within the week.
     </p>
     <p>
       I am looking to replace the XML -> Bean mapping mechanism used in
       Maven with the Betwixt package in the Commons sandbox. Betwixt provides
       full roundtrip mapping and it is generally more configurable. I am also
       trying to get rid of as much code in Stratum as possible and go with
       existing or better code so I'm going to try and get rid of the
       homegrown mapper that I made.
     </p>
   </section>

   <section name="Turbine 3.0">
     <p>
       There will be a full roadmap for Turbine 3.0 this Friday. I will try
       and outline all the things I think are required for Turbine 3.0 to
       be successful and all the items that need to be taken care of in
       order to get there. I will try to make the roadmap highly detailed.
     </p>
   </section>
  </body>
</document>
