<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
 Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
-->

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Turbine</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Apache Turbine Web Application Framework">

  <p>
    Turbine is a servlet based framework that allows experienced Java
    developers to quickly build web applications. Turbine allows you
    to use personalize the web sites and to use user logins to restrict
    access to parts of your application.
  </p>

  <p>
    Turbine is a matured and well established framework that is used as
    the base of many other projects (like e.g. the excellent <a
    href="http://portals.apache.org/jetspeed-1/">Jetspeed 1</a>
    Portals framework.
  </p>

  <p>
    Turbine is an excellent choice for developing applications that make use of a
    services-oriented architecture. Some of the functionality
    provided with Turbine includes a security management system, a
    scheduling service, XML-defined form validation server,
    and an XML-RPC service for web services.  It is a
    simple task to create new services particular to your application.
  </p>

  <p>
    The Turbine core is free of any dependency on a presentation layer
    technology. Both JavaServer Pages (JSP) and
    <a href="http://velocity.apache.org/engine/">Velocity</a> are supported
    inside Turbine.  For developers already familiar with JSP, or have
    existing JSP tag libraries, Turbine offers support for the Sun standard.
    Velocity is the favorite view technology of most users of the Turbine
    framework; try it out and see if Velocity can help you develop your
    web applications faster and work more easily with non-programming designers.
  </p>

  <p>
    Turbine is developed in an open, participatory environment and
    released under the <a href="common/license.html">Apache
    Software License</a>. Turbine is intended to be a collaboration of the
    best-of-breed developers from around the world.  We invite you to
    participate in this open development project.  To learn more about getting
    involved, <a href="how-to-help.html">look at our &quot;How to Help&quot; pages</a>.
  </p>

</section>

<section name="Turbine Versions">
  <p>
    Turbine comes in two shapes which both have their advantages:

  <ul>
    <li><a href="turbine/turbine-2.3.3/">Turbine 2.3.3</a> is
    the version you should use when either migrating from an older version of
    Turbine or starting a project based on a release version of the Turbine
    framework.  The 2.3 branch of Turbine is actively maintained and we have started
    the <a href="turbine/development/turbine-2.3">2.3.3</a> release
    cycle. So we are going to have a maintenance relase soon.</li>
    
    <li>While <a href="turbine/development/turbine-2.4/">Turbine 2.4</a> is
    the shape of things to come, it is currently in a state of flux and for now
    we recommend that you stick with the 2.3.x release series.  Turbine 2.4 uses
    next generation technologies like an <a href="http://avalon.apache.org/">
    Avalon-based</a> container and decoupled components from the
    <a href="fulcrum/">Fulcrum</a> sub-project of Turbine (most of benefits of
    these enhancements will be realized in the forthcoming
    <a href="turbine/development/turbine-2.3">2.3.3</a> release). One significant
    change in 2.4 that is unlikely to be back ported to the 2.3 branch is the
    introduction of a pipeline concept that allows you to define via an XML file
    all the stages for processing a request.  Note that at time of writing there
    are a number of fixes and enhancements that have been implemented in the 2.3
    branch that need to be ported forward to 2.4 before it can move forward.
    There are also issues relating to the separation of various services out to
    Fulcrum components that need to be resolved.  For now, to use 2.4 you need
    to build your own jars from the Subversion repository and tolerate the inevitable
    api changes that will occur while the aforementioned issues are addressed.</li>
  </ul>
  </p>
</section>

<section name="Sub Projects">

<p></p>
<ul>
  <li>
    <a href="/fulcrum/">Fulcrum</a> is a collection of services originally
    developed as part of Turbine, but now decoupled and usable in any environment
    that supports <a href="http://avalon.apache.org/">Avalon</a> components.
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="/meta/">META</a> (Maven Environment for Turbine Applications) helps
    you to write Turbine applications.
  </li>
</ul>
</section>

<section name="Turbine Alumni">

<p>
 As a longtime, but now ex-member of the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/">Jakarta Project</a>, Turbine has influenced
quite a number of projects:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    <a href="http://db.apache.org/torque/">Torque</a> is a persistence
    layer originally developed as part of Turbine.  Torque is now
    decoupled and part of the <a href="http://db.apache.org/">Apache Database Project</a>.
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven</a> is an advanced Java
    Project Management tool originally developed out of the frustration with the
    Turbine build process. Maven is now a toplevel Apache project, residing at <a
    href="http://maven.apache.org/">maven.apache.org</a>.
  </li>
  <li>
    In addition, Turbine has spawned a number of <a href="http://commons.apache.org/">Commons</a>
    components like <a href="http://commons.apache.org/configuration/">Commons configuration</a> or
    <a href="http://commons.apache.org/email/">Commons EMail</a>.
  </li>
</ul>
</section>

</body>
</document>
